THIS STORY IS A FICION, AND ALL NAMES OF FIGURES ND ORGANIZATIONS ARE FICTITIOUS.
（本作所有人物、組織名均為虛構）
MOREOVER, THE STORY HAS NO RELATION TO REAL-LIFE INCIDENTS AND EVENTS.
（與任何特定事件或現象無關）
Oh, right. I'm home.
對了，我回到家了
My hair's so sticky…
頭髮好黏
Old man must be…
老爹…
At the farm.
在田裡吧
He's not young,
他也不年輕了
so I'd like him to stop working at the farm…
雖然希望他別再到田裡工作了
But he sure loves making medicine out of herbs he grew himself,
但他就是愛用 自己親手栽的藥草來製藥
that old man.
老爹真是的
You'll break it.
會被妳敲壞的
I don't know you. Are you an outside apprentice?
我沒見過妳 是別家的見習娼妓小丫頭嗎？
-The old man… -Come!
-老爹… -快過來！
Big Sis!
大姐
I brought the apothecary!
我把藥師帶來了！
-Quickly! -This smell…!
-快點 -這個味道…
Ms. Apothecary! I made them vomit it out, but…
藥師姑娘，我幫他們催吐了，但是…
Not yet!
還不夠
He's not breathing.
男的沒呼吸了
Her breath is weak too.
女的呼吸也很弱
I'll check whether there's any vomit in his throat.
先確認他們喉嚨裡是否還有嘔吐物
-You check her. -Yes!
-女的麻煩妳了 -好
He has no pulse. Nothing in his throat, either.
沒有脈搏，喉嚨裡沒有東西
Just saliva.
只有唾液
Bring some water!
去拿些水來
Don't make them drink water!
先不要喝水
Charcoal. Bring some charcoal!
木炭，去準備些木炭
Yes, ma'am!
好的
What is all this, so early in the morning?
一大清早的，到底怎麼回事啊？
I want to take a bath…
好想洗澡
Thank you, Ms. Apothecary. They're both stable now.
謝謝妳，藥師姑娘 他們兩人都穩定下來了
-Oh, leave that. -Even the vomit?
-先別動那些東西 -嘔吐物也別動嗎？
-There might be poison left over. -Poison…
-裡面可能有殘留的毒物 -毒物…
I'll prepare some tea.
我去準備茶水
The sick people were a courtesan and her customer.
倒下的是娼妓和她的恩客
The room was filled with the scent of alcohol and tobacco.
屋裡滿是酒和菸草的味道
Two liquor bottles.
有兩個酒瓶
Shattered glass cups.
破掉的玻璃杯
Is this… wheat stalk?
這是…麥稈嗎？
A smoking pipe, and tobacco leaves.
菸管和菸草
What an elaborate act this is.
真是弄出了麻煩事
Here's some charcoal.
這個，木炭
Can you bring a wood tablet and something to write with?
嗯，接著拿一片木簡 和書寫的東西過來
What?
什麼？
The old man should be at the farm
南邊外牆旁有塊田
by the southern outer walls.
我家老爹應該就在那裡
Can you bring him too?
再請妳把他帶過來
I got it.
知道了
You're late, old man.
老爹，你真慢啊
This girl was concerned for my legs.
因為這孩子顧慮著我的腳啊
I crushed the charcoal.
我已經把木炭搗碎了
I'll mix it with the herbs and have them take it right away.
嗯，快點和藥草混合讓他們服下吧
Can you drink this?
妳能喝嗎？
And him?
他呢？
He's okay. He took the medicine.
他沒事，他也喝了藥
I guess your treatment was all right.
處理的方法還算可以吧
Just "all right"?
只是“還算可以”啊？
Old man is someone who can learn two or three things
老爹是知道一絲訊息後
out of a single piece of information.
就能明白兩、三件事情的人
What poison did you think this was?
妳覺得這是哪種毒物？
Here it comes!
來了
Old man tries to teach me lessons like this sometimes.
老爹有時候會像這樣，指點我學習
Tobacco leaves are poisonous.
菸草有劇毒
This is what they'd use for a suicide pact.
要殉情的話，我想這個很適合
I hear you didn't make them drink water.
妳似乎沒讓她們喝水，對吧？
That would have reverse effects.
喝水會適得其反吧？
That's true.
說得不錯
Gastric fluid can prevent the absorption of poison,
胃液有能夠抑制毒物吸收的效果
so in that case, water wouldn't help.
這種情況下，喝水就沒有幫助
But what if this was dissolved in water in the first place?
但如果毒物一開始就溶在水裡呢？
There are no leaves in the vomit!
嘔吐物裡沒有菸草
I missed it. Am I still half-asleep?
我沒注意到，我當時還沒睡醒嗎？
If the poison was dissolved in water, it's better to dilute it.
如果毒物溶於水裡的話 稀釋就會是比較好的作法
All right. Now I know.
好，記起來了
I'm sorry about this.
真是抱歉
Offering tea sweets reserved for guests?
用給客人的茶點招待我們
They're quite generous.
他們真是大方呢
I see.
原來如此
They use this to prevent lipstick stains on the cups.
他們用這個來避免唇印留在杯子上
You really helped us a lot.
真的是幫了我們大忙
This is a mere token, but…
一點心意，不成敬意
-No, I can't accept that… -Old man.
-不，我不能收… -老爹
Can you afford rent to Grams this month?
你這個月付得出房租給老鴇嗎？
I happily accept.
那麼…
Geez. This old man…
天啊，老爹真是的…
This instance was
這次的騷動
a classic case of a suicide pact. Not uncommon here.
是殉情事件吧，在煙花巷並不稀奇
A woman with a long term of service
付不出贖身費用的男子
and a man that can't afford to buy her out.
碰上賣身期限未盡的女子
Couples like that always have one plan.
大概就只會想到這種事了
But that man… He was dressed in expensive clothing.
但那個男人 身上穿著相當高貴的布料
He has a handsome face.
長相也算俊俏
He doesn't seem to have a problem with money or women.
不像是會為財色所困的樣子
Though I'm making assumptions. Old man wouldn't like that.
但用偏見來思考，老爹會生氣的吧
He doesn't seem the type to take poison for his future with a courtesan…
他看起來不像是會擔心 和娼妓沒有未來而服毒的人
I'm going to go check.
我去看看情況
The man's condition was more serious.
男子的狀況比較嚴重…
What are you doing?!
妳在做什麼？
Don't get in my way! Bastards like him should die!
別來妨礙我 像他這種混蛋死了最好！
Ouch…
好痛
What are you two doing?
妳們兩個在做什麼？
Ms. Apothecary, can I talk to you for a minute?
藥師姑娘，方便跟妳說兩句話嗎？
He was a very problematic customer.
那位客人本來就是個問題人物
He would say sweet words to courtesans,
他會不斷對娼妓甜言蜜語
act as if he were buying them out,
一副會幫她們贖身的樣子
then abandon them once he got bored.
但等膩了之後就拋棄她們
He incurred a lot of wrath.
四處不斷招致怨恨
He'd almost get stabbed by an enraged woman,
曾經差點被憤恨難平的女子刺殺
or get poisoned.
也曾經被下毒過
But he's spoiled by his father, who's a wealthy merchant.
但他的富商父親相當寵溺他
Every time, he would resolve problems with money.
每每出了事就用金錢解決
Recently,
最近
he would come to brothels accompanied by guards that he asked his parents for.
他還向父親要求帶著護衛來青樓
Her older sister was also abandoned by that man.
這孩子的姊姊也是被那人拋棄
She was looking forward to living with him,
她本來還很期待贖身後 跟他一起生活，非常開心
but he took it back on the day of the buyout.
但他卻在要贖身那一天反悔了
That's why she couldn't forgive him.
所以她才無法原諒他
She was attached to the courtesan that drank the poison today, so…
她也很黏今天一起 喝下毒藥的那名娼妓
So I'm supposed to pretend I didn't see this?
所以要我裝作沒這回事？
Customers like that shouldn't be permitted to enter.
那種客人禁止他出入就好了吧
It was her that fell for him.
那名娼妓迷戀著他呀
And it led to today's suicide pact incident?
所以才導致了今天的殉情事件？
That's definitely a bad look for the brothel.
青樓這邊想必也很頭痛吧
They must've been so generous with us
也難怪他們會如此款待
because we prevented the death of a wealthy merchant's son at their business.
因為我們沒讓富商的兒子 死在他們自己的店裡
And that's why…
結果…
This situation must've felt so unjust to this girl.
卻讓這孩子覺得豈有此理吧
I understand.
我明白了
I just happened to be back home today.
今天是我碰巧回來了
But if she runs errands every day,
如果她平常總是幫忙跑腿的話
she might have known the hours that old man is out.
也許就知道老爹不在家的時間
Normally, one would call a doctor.
一般這種狀況，會去叫醫生才對
If she purposefully came to call on an absent apothecary…
她卻特意來找不在家的藥師
That apprentice girl… She's small, but frightening.
那位見習娼妓小丫頭 年紀雖小，想法卻很可怕呢
What a situation for you, after you came all this way.
妳好不容易回來一趟 怎麼會發生這種事呢？
Old man. Show me the cash.
老爹，剛剛的袋子讓我看一下
Yup. There's money inside.
確實有放錢
Along with an added amount of hush money.
還加上額外的封口費
But something about this bothers me.
但總覺得有點在意
From what I hear, the man doesn't seem the delicate type.
就剛剛的說法 那男人應該相當難應付才是
Would a man like that make a suicide pact for a woman he loves?
他會為因為迷戀那女子 而一起殉情嗎？
Was it a forced suicide pact?
還是情殺呢？
But would a man who had been poisoned before be so careless…?
但一個曾被下過毒的男子 會這麼不小心嗎？
Maomao. I told you, don't make assumptions.
貓貓，我說過不能憑著臆測推論吧？
You already know the truth, don't you?
老爹你已經知道真相了，對吧？
Let me remember.
快想起來
What was at the scene?
現場有什麼東西？
Did I miss anything?
我漏掉了什麼嗎？
Tobacco leaves are poisonous.
“菸草有劇毒
This is what they'd use for a suicide pact.
要殉情的話，我想這個很適合”
But what if this was dissolved in water in the first place?
“但如果毒物 一開始就溶在水裡呢？”
It was her that fell for him.
“那名娼妓迷戀著他呀”
Bastards like him should die!
“像他這種混蛋死了最好！”
She was attached to the courtesan that drank the poison today, so…
“她也很黏今天一起 喝下毒藥的那名娼妓”
I see. They use this to prevent lipstick stains on the cups.
“原來如此 他們用這個來避免唇印留在杯子上”
This wasn't a suicide pact.
這不是殉情
It was murder.
是謀殺
Substance dissolved in water… Wheat stalk…
溶在水裡的東西、麥稈…
Two different types of alcohol…
兩種不同類型顏色的酒…
It's all over, all right?
事情已經結束了
I know that.
我知道
A murder, not a suicide pact.
不是殉情，是謀殺
And the murderer was the courtesan.
而且想殺人的是娼妓這方
The murder weapon was alcohol poisoned with tobacco.
用來殺人的，是用菸草下毒的酒
But how did she make the man drink the poison, when he was so cautious
但要如何讓帶著護衛
of his safety that he had personal guards?
戒心變得甚重的男人，喝下毒酒呢？
It's quite simple.
很簡單
She could drink it herself.
只要試毒給他看就行了
If the courtesan is safe, the man would drink the alcohol, too.
如果娼妓沒事 那個男人就會把酒喝下
But if she actually drank the poisonous alcohol, she'd be in danger.
但如果她真的喝下了毒酒 便不可能安然無恙
That's why she used those tools.
所以她用了一些工具
Two types of alcohol and one cup.
兩種不同的酒和一個杯子
Different types of alcohol differ in richness and density.
不同種類的酒有不同的濃度和重量
If you pour light alcohol slowly on top of heavy alcohol,
只要在厚重的酒上方 慢慢倒入質地較輕的酒
it will create aesthetically pleasing layers.
就會形成美麗的層次
If she performed this trick as a way to please customers,
如果用來當作取悅客人的小把戲
the courtesan could drink only the bottom layer
娼妓就能在不引起懷疑的情況下
using the wheat stalk.
用麥稈只喝了下層的酒給對方看
The courtesan also drank the top layer alcohol.
娼妓也喝了上層的酒
Only a small amount, so that she wouldn't die.
但只喝了不會致死的量
The plan would be pointless if she died as well.
如果自己也死了，可就得不償失了
She calculated the timing
她應該是盤算好
so that he would die, and she would survive.
能害死男人，自己也能夠活下來
That's why it happened in the morning.
所以在早上做了這件事吧
And conveniently, someone found them like that.
然後又正好有人發現他們出事了
She is delicate,
雖然看似纖弱
but tough at the same time.
但也十分強悍呢
What are you doing, Big Sis?
大姐，妳在做什麼？
You have to stay asleep!
妳得好好休息才行
The apprentice's actions were a bit off.
見習娼妓小丫頭的行為有點奇怪
She went to the apothecary
為了讓男子回天乏術
and not the doctor so that the man would run out of time.
她刻意不去找醫生，而是來找藥師
She took her time to bring old man.
把老爹帶來時也花了一些時間
Was she not concerned for her "Big Sis"?
她不擔心她的“大姐”嗎？
Did she not think that just like her
還是跟親姊姊那時候一樣
actual older sister, someone close to her could die again?
沒想過又會有親近之人逝去呢？
It's almost as if she knew she wouldn't die.
就像是知道那女子不會死才這麼行動
Could be. Or I'm just overthinking things.
可能想太多了吧
And the courtesan who was oddly sympathetic to the apprentice.
還有那名娼妓 極度地同情這名見習娼妓小丫頭
The granny who paid us well.
以及給了豐厚報酬的老鴇
Anyone can seem suspicious if you view them that way.
一旦懷疑起來 就覺得全都是些可疑的事情了
Could it be that everyone was…
難道說每個人都…
I can't be making assumptions.
不能憑著臆測推論嘛
I wanted to come back here for a long time.
我一直想回來的煙花巷
But here's no different than the rear palace.
本質上其實與後宮並無不同
It's a flower garden, a bird cage.
既是花園，也是鳥籠
All become poisoned by the air in this trapped environment.
所有人都被關在這當中 被這裡的空氣毒害
And the courtesans, by eating others' poisons,
娼妓也因著吃下周圍的毒物
themselves become sweet poison.
讓自己也變成了甜蜜的毒藥
I don't know what will happen to that courtesan.
不知道那名娼妓會發生什麼事
The spoiled son could
被寵壞的兒子
claim and complain that he got poisoned,
也許會一狀告上官府 說自己被下毒也不一定
or it could be that
或者剛好相反
the brothel threatens him for ruining their merchandise.
青樓可能會說他糟蹋了商品 藉此來威脅他
It doesn't matter either way.
怎麼樣都好
If we troubled our minds about these things,
如果一直掛念這種事情的話
we'd never survive this town.
可沒辦法在這街上活下去
Maomao!
貓貓
Big Sis Meimei!
梅梅姐姐
You're already going back to the palace?
妳這麼快就要回後宮了？
I still have a year left in my term of service.
我的期限還有一年
And if I quit my job, I'd cause trouble to others.
如果我辭退了那份工作 會給別人添麻煩
I see. But you only just got home.
是喔，妳好不容易才回來了
Everyone was so worried after you went missing suddenly.
妳突然失蹤之後，每個人都好擔心
Pairin, Juka, and Granny too.
白鈴、女華，婆婆都是
But they didn't mention that at all…
咦？她們完全沒提…
Everyone acted like nothing was wrong, right?
大家都和平常一樣，對吧？
It's because you came back.
那是因為妳回來了
I see.
是喔
Did that make you sad?
真是的，覺得寂寞了嗎？
It's okay, baby!
好乖
Stop that, Big Sis Meimei!
別這樣啦，梅梅姐姐
Maomao. Did you go to the annex?
貓貓，妳去過別館了嗎？
Yeah. I'll go later.
我等等會去
Be careful, all right?
小心點
You too, old man.
老爹也是
I'll be off.
我走囉
My three-day homecoming
三天的返家日
ended before I realized.
轉眼間就結束了
You're already going home? What a disappointment!
妳要回去啦？真是太可惜了
Right, Sir Lihaku?
對吧，李白大人？
Yes! What a disappointment, truly!
對呀，真的是太可惜了
Looks like he enjoyed his time here.
看來做了一場好夢呢
Once you taste the sweet nectar of the heavens,
一旦嚐過天堂的甘露後
you can't come back to earth.
就回不到人間了
He'll continue to get squeezed out so that he neither lives nor dies.
她們一定會不斷壓榨他 弄得他半死不活吧
Even so,
話是這麼說
I'm the one paying for what the advance payment couldn't cover.
訂金不足的部分可是我補上的啊
Call me when you're back, all right?
妳要回來的時候給個聯絡啊
Now I know exactly where I'm selling myself to next.
拜這所賜，看來下個 賣身場所在哪也決定了
Why is he glaring at me like that?
他為什麼死盯著這邊看？
I'll get out of here quickly.
還是快點離開吧
I'm going to go change now.
我去換衣服了
-Tell us… -Everything…
-等等 -把一切
Later!
都告訴我們喔
I'll be waiting for you in the reception room.
我在前廳等著妳
Excuse me.
打擾了
His attitude is worse than usual.
感覺他的態度比平常更糟糕
Am I just imagining things?
是錯覺嗎？
I hope that's the case. We'll put it that way.
應該是錯覺，就當作是錯覺吧
But… why is it just the two of us?
但是，為什麼只有我們兩人？
I hear you visited home.
我聽說妳回家了
Yes.
對
How was it?
還好嗎？
Everyone seemed to be doing well. I was glad.
每個人似乎都過得很好，我很高興
-I see. -Yes, sir.
-這樣啊 -是的
And what kind of man is this Lihaku?
這個李白是何許人也？
Huh?
什麼？
He's my surety.
他是我的保人
Why does he know his name?
他為什麼知道李白的名字？
Do you know what that means?
妳知道那代表什麼意思嗎？
Yes. He has to be of a certain status.
知道，若不是有一定地位的高官的話
Otherwise, he can't be my surety.
是沒辦法當保人的
What?
什麼啦？
Did he give you a hair clip?
妳收了他的髮簪嗎？
He was handing several of them out.
他發了很多支
It was an obligatory gift to me.
是做人情而已
You mean to tell me I lost to an obligatory gift?
妳意思是說 我輸給了一個做人情的？
I gave you one also.
我應該也有給妳髮簪
But you never talked to me.
但妳卻完全沒向我開口
"I"? What?
“我”？怎麼搞的？
So he's in a bad mood because I didn't propose an offer to him?
所以他心情不好 是因為我沒請他幫忙嗎？
That's very strange.
真不可思議
It's better not to get involved in troublesome things.
明明別扯上麻煩事比較好
He's always bored.
還是因為他閒著沒事
Does he want attention, even when it's troublesome?
所以有麻煩事也沒關係嗎？
I'm so sorry, sir.
真是非常抱歉
I could not think of a worthy payment
我想不出能讓壬氏大人滿足的謝禮
that would satisfy you.
來答謝您的幫忙
What payment?
什麼謝禮？
Did you make this "payment" to this Lihaku man?
妳給了那個叫李白的傢伙謝禮嗎？
Of course. He seemed happy with his one night of dreams.
是的，他似乎很開心能享受一夜春宵
One night?
一夜春宵？
He seemed extremely satisfied.
他看起來相當滿意
I'm glad I worked hard too.
這樣我的努力也值得了
What are you doing?
您做什麼啊？
Use this, before it stains.
趁還沒留下污漬，用這個擦吧
Excuse me, sir.
失禮了
You should wash this right away.
趕快把這件衣服送去洗比較好喔
I'll carry this teacup away, so don't touch it.
我會把茶碗收拾乾淨，請不要碰喔
Excuse me.
小的先告退了
PREVIEW OF NEXT EPISODE
（下集預告）
Next episode, "Suicide or Murder?"
下一集，《自殺還是他殺？》
Subtitle translation by: Yukimi Ohashi
字幕翻譯：歐德慧